原视频名：When a Volcano Erupts Under Your Neighbor's House - Visiting the site of Hawaii's 2018 Eruption.
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/RRuR3nB1RKos
原视频发布日期：20210810
字幕翻译：邺寒_Link，校对：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
氦 我是Scott Manley
And I am standing in front of ʻAhuʻailāʻau
我正站在ʻAhuʻailāʻau的前面
which used to be known as fissure eight three years ago
三年前 它被称为8号裂缝
when it was spewing lava hundreds of feet into the air
当它将熔岩喷到数百米高的空中时
and basically laying waste to this whole neighborhood.
基本上把整个区域都毁掉了
It is an amazing and weird place to be with a wreckage
这是一个令人惊奇和奇怪的地方 上面是残垣断壁
and just new earth underneath it.
下面是新的土壤
It's three years old this this rock that I'm standing on this.
我现在就站在这块 三年前那次活动形成的岩石上
Well it's not even rock.
其实 它甚至不是岩石
It's just compressed spatter tephra is what they call it.
这只是压缩的火山喷溅物 他们是这样称呼它的
Yeah let's explore.
好 让我们来探索一下
When I was in Hawaii a couple of months ago
几个月前 当我在夏威夷的时候
one of the places I really wanted to explore was this.
我最想探索的地方之一就是这个
This is known as fissure eight.
这就是所谓的8号裂缝
It is one of many lava fissures that opened up in the middle of the neighborhood of Leilani Estates.
它是莱拉尼庄园区域附近众多熔岩裂缝中的一个
A lot of those in those trees next to this area.
这个区域旁边有许多树木
You can see houses.
你可以看到房屋
Some of them butt up right against the lava field
其中一些房子紧靠着熔岩区
but fissure 8 was the largest of many.
8号裂缝是众多熔岩裂缝中最大的一个
It would ultimately throw out hundreds of thousands of tons of lava
它最终抛出了数十万吨熔岩
that would flow eight miles to the sea and create new areas of land.
这些熔岩在大海上流动了13千米 形成了新的土地区域
During the two months it was active.
在它活跃的两个月里
This fissure emitted more lava than the rest of the mountain does in five years.
这个裂缝喷出的熔岩比山脉里其他地方五年总共喷出的还要多
And it drained so much lava out of the mountain
它从山中排出了如此多的熔岩
that the reserves were depleted to the extent
储备被耗尽 以至于
that essentially it brought an end to an eruption which had been ongoing since the 1980s.
从本质上讲 它结束了自1980年代以来一直在进行的火山爆发
And now years after the activity has stopped
而现在 在活动停止多年后
it's possible for adventurous people to go and visit this area that was once a community.
富有冒险精神的人们 可以去参观这个曾经是有人居住的区域
You can climb to the top of this fissure which was laid down and built up by the eruption from it.
你可以爬到这个由它自身的喷发而形成的顶部
But first I want to rewind the clock
但首先我想讲讲历史
and talk about the geology that drove this eruption.
谈谈推动这次火山爆发的地质学原理
2018年火山国家公园
I previously visited the big island of Hawaii in 2018
我曾在2018年访问过夏威夷火山大岛
and there had been some significant changes to the way Kilauea was erupting.
当时 基拉韦厄的喷发方式已经发生了一些重大变化
There was a lava lake at the top of the mountain Halemaʻumaʻu crater.
在Halemaʻumaʻu火山口的山顶有一个熔岩湖
This was unusual since 1983
这是不寻常的 因为自1983年后
most of the eruption had occurred through event called Pu'u'ō'ō which was further down to the east
大部分的喷发都发生在东面更远处的Pu'u'ō'ō地区
but something had changed and the lava was backing up and reaching the top of the mountain.
但情况发生了变化 熔岩正在倒流 到达山顶
You have to understand underneath the volcano there are channels and reservoirs
你必须知道 在火山下面有一些渠道和熔岩室
where molten magma collects and moves around.
熔化的岩浆在那里汇聚和移动
So with magma being pushed up to the top of the mountain
因此 随着岩浆被推上山顶
that increased the pressure and that forces some of these channels around apart
增加了压力 扩张周围的一些通道
and you start getting cracks forming which cause earthquakes and eruptions.
并开始形成裂缝 导致地震和喷发
And there was a 6.9 magnitude earthquake which be seen to be the major trigger for everything.
有一次6.9级的地震 被认为是一切事件的导火索
To give you an idea of how big an effect this was
为了让你知道这有多大的影响
this diagram shows you how far the land moved on the surface
这张图显示了陆块移动了多远
and in places the island moved several meters southwards in a time measured in seconds.
在一些地方 岛屿在以秒计算的时间内向南移动了数米
And that unblocked the channels the lava was using to move around
这就疏通了熔岩移动的通道
and in the lower East Rift Zone cracks began to open emitting steam and then later lava.
在东裂谷区的下部 裂缝开始打开 排放出蒸汽 然后是熔岩
And interestingly the first lava that came out was very thick and sticky and slow moving
有趣的是 第一次喷出的熔岩非常厚实 粘稠 移动缓慢
and this was because it was actually magma from a 1950s eruption.
这是因为它实际上是20世纪50年代喷发的岩浆
There had been an eruption in the area and it had stopped
该地区曾有过一次喷发 尽管已经停止了
but some of the magma was still sitting underground slowly cooling
但一些岩浆仍在地下慢慢冷却
but now this new eruption was happening it was getting pushed out
但现在新的喷发正在发生 这些老的熔岩被推了出来
and eventually the slow-moving lava would be replaced by fresh fast-moving lava
最终 缓慢移动的熔岩被快速移动的新熔岩所取代
and that lava was actually being fed from the top of the mountain.
而这些熔岩实际上是由山顶的熔岩湖供给的
That lake that I had seen up there was sinking down into the mountain
这个湖泊正在向下沉去
draining out through the location far to the east.
从远东边的地方排出去
And without the mass of that lava supporting the top of the mountain
如果没有熔岩的质量支撑着山顶
it then began to collapse in on itself and the crater got larger and larger
它就开始自我坍塌 火山口变得越来越大
destabilizing the crater room
破坏了火山口室的稳定
and that meant that the Jaggar Museum and volcanic observatory which was on the rim is now closed.
这意味着位于火山口上的Jaggar博物馆和火山观测站现在已经关闭
This is a video I took in 2018 from the look out there.
这是我2018年面朝那里拍摄的视频
This is now closed
现在 这里已经关闭了
and actually that crater behind them would be completely collapsed in.
而实际上他们身后的那个火山口会完全塌陷进去
So I love Volcanoes National Park.
所以我喜欢火山国家公园
It is amazing.
它是惊人的
But I wanted to find a more raw and uncurated experience
但我想找到一种更原始的 未被探索的体验
and so I drove down to Leilani estates.
所以我开车去了莱拉尼庄园
I found some locals who do give tours.
我找到了一些从事旅游行业的当地人
Actually there's several companies that give tours.
事实上 有几家公司提供旅游服务
There's like locals who will just like show you the stuff.
有一些当地人会带你参观这些东西
You can actually have vacation rentals in the area
实际上 你可以在该地区租到度假屋
and then there are the professional tour companies that charge people hundreds of dollars
还有一些专业的旅游公司 向人们收取数百美元的费用
and put up no trespassing signs to stop other people coming in.
并挂上禁止进入的牌子来阻止散客进入
It is important to remember though that this is essentially a residential neighborhood.
但重要的是 其本质上是一个住宅区
Sure they were large one acre lots but people were living here when the fissure are opened up
在这片一英亩大的土地上 当裂缝被打开之前 人们就住在这里
so it was a series of fissures actually that ran sort of south east away from the volcano.
所以它是一系列的裂缝 向东南方向延伸 逐渐远离火山
This was called the East Rift Zone.
这被称为东裂谷区
And in some areas they just start opening up and you have small patches
在一些地区 裂缝刚刚开始打开 只是一些很小的地方
and then you go down to fissure eight and it just turns into a giant lava field.
然后你走到第八条裂缝 它就变成了一个巨大的熔岩区
But there are people still living in some of these areas.
但是有些地区仍然有人生活在那里
Some of these houses that have been spared the most of the damage.
这些房子中的一些幸免于大部分伤害
And if you walk around the neighborhood there are lots of signs for private property.
而且如果你在附近走走 有很多私人财产的标志
Even on the properties that are destroyed.
甚至在那些被破坏的房产上
I mean yeah people still own this land
我的意思是 人们仍然拥有这些土地
although many have sold to government programs
尽管许多人已经将土地卖给了政府项目
designed to help people who have had a volcano open up underneath their house.
项目旨在帮助那些在火山口上面拥有房子的人们
So this is basically going next door and this is one of the flows right.
所以这基本上是流向隔壁 属于其中的一个流向吧？
Right.
对
So it was a chain of fissures running off in one direction and this is what we got.
所以它是一连串的裂缝向一个方向延伸 这就是我们得到的东西
I know that basically they filled the lava lake at the top of Kilauea
我知道 基本上它们填满了基拉韦厄顶部的熔岩湖
and then it began to just drain out and they weren't sure where it was going initially.
然后它开始流出 他们最初并不确定它的去向
Right.
对
But there was lava coming out down here.
但是有熔岩从这里流出来
Right and so it came out down here that was why it was
对 所以它从这里流出来 这就是它的原因
That was there like that wall made it.
就在那里 就像那堵墙一样
Oh yeah there's an actual handmade lava wall in there
哦 是的 那里有一个真正的手工制作的熔岩墙
That has a water heater there.
那里有一个热水器
There's a water heater back there right.
后面有一个热水器 对
There's probably a lot of things in there.
那里面可能有很多东西
I'd really far be interested to do archaeology underneath lava flows.
我真的很想在熔岩流下面做考古
Oh there's a barbecue still sitting there as well.
哦 还有一个烧烤架也还在那里放着
Yeah I think that was there.
是的 我想那是在那里
A nice gas grill.
一个漂亮的燃气烤架
Could be.
可能是
So yeah basically this road was had lava on it.
所以 实际上这条路是有些熔岩留在上面的
And they just scraped it off broke it up and it's a road again.
他们只是把它刮掉了 把它打碎了 又成了一条路
One of the starkest examples of the sort of randomness with which this destruction was laid out
最明显的例子之一是这所房子 (表明了)它的破坏是随机的
was this house which has somebody living in it
这座房子里住着人
and the neighbor where the house was basically destroyed by a fissure opening up underneath it
邻居的房子基本上被它下面的熔岩裂缝摧毁了
and spewing lava.
并喷出熔岩
Now in this case the house was generally destroyed by the fire
现在 在这种情况下 房子一般都被火烧毁了
but they did have lava in their garage which destroyed their cars.
但他们的车库中也渗出了熔岩 摧毁了他们的汽车
And while the rock in the surface has cooled down to manageable levels
虽然表面的岩石已经冷却到可控水平
there's still a lot of hot rock underneath the surface
但在地表下仍有大量的热岩
and that heat is spreading out sideways
热量正在向侧面扩散
and sterilizing the soil that is near to these areas.
并使这些地区附近的土壤变得贫瘠
Around the back of the house though they still have a nice lawn there.
不过在房子的后面 他们仍然有一个漂亮的草坪
They do have some problems mowing the lawn
他们在修剪草坪时确实有一些问题
because there's a giant fissure in it which is like eight feet wide near the street.
因为那里有一个巨大的裂缝 靠近街道的地方有2.4米宽
The house is perfectly serviceable.
房子是完全可以使用的
People live there.
人们住在那里
And they still work on the garden.
而且他们还在花园里工作
It just is a garden with some very interesting features in it.
它只是一个花园 里面有一些非常有趣的特征
But extreme gardening had a place here long before the eruption.
但在火山爆发之前 这里就有了很好的园艺
There was a one nursery here which specialized in carnivorous plants.
这里有一个苗圃 专门种植食肉植物
And apparently it was world famous renowned
显然 它是世界著名的
but unfortunately it was right underneath or right on top of where fissure 8 opened up
但不幸的是 它就在8号裂缝的上面
and now it is completely buried by the eruption.
现在它被火山爆发完全掩埋了
But the owner still owns the property
但业主仍然拥有这处房产
and just last year at christmas he basically paid some people
就在去年圣诞节 他花钱请了一些人
to bulldoze a road along the original route that the street followed.
沿着街道原来的路线铲除了一条路
You can see in this photo here that was sent to me on twitter.
你可以从这张照片中看到 这是在推特上发给我的
I mean seriously good luck to the person behind this because that's pretty badass.
说真的 祝这背后的人好运 因为那里时常会有一些危险
And conveniently this road also makes it quite easy to get close to fissure eight
而且 这条道路也很方便 可以很容易地接近8号裂缝
and because this is a hazardous area some of the places are collapsing.
因为这是一个危险区域 有些地方正在坍塌
On one side it was all lava flows and that stuff has its own texture
一边是熔岩流 那东西有它自己的结构
but on the side you tend to approach it from these are tephra fields.
但在你接近它的那一面 这些都是火山灰土形成的区域
This is where the lava has been fountaining up in the air
这就是熔岩在空中喷涌的地方
and then hardening and then falling back down and it falls like snow.
然后变硬 再落下 像雪一样落下
And if you go off of a trail that is well worn.
如果你离开了一条铺得很好的小路
You can very quickly find yourself digging into like two or three feet of basically loosely bound rock
你很快就会发现自己来到了约一米高的松散的岩石上
so tephra is basically between volcanic ash which is very fine
火山灰土基本上是介于火山灰和火山弹之间 前者非常细小
and volcanic bombs which are like things the size of your fist.
而后者差不多就有你拳头的大小
These are bits of gravel bits of other material.
这些都是碎石的碎片和其他物质的碎片
It's frequently got a lot of gas in it.
它经常有很多气体在里面
It's very light and very fragile
它非常轻 非常脆弱
and it comes in a million different colors.
而且它有一百万种不同的颜色
Well maybe not a million
好吧 也许不是一百万种
but the mineralogy is really important to figuring out the temperature that the lava was when it was exuded.
但矿物学对于弄清熔岩流出时的温度非常重要
Also you'll sometimes find well the remains of dead things.
另外 你有时会发现死物的残骸
Thankfully there were no human casualties with this eruption.
值得庆幸的是 这次火山爆发没有造成人员伤亡
Just a lot of properties destroyed and carnivorous plants.
只是有很多财产被毁 还有食肉植物
Three years on from the eruption there's still a lot of heat here.
喷发三年后 这里仍然很热
And a lot of that is visible because it's very wet.
因为这里非常潮湿 所以可以清楚的看出来
The rain comes and it seeps into the ground
雨水来到这里 渗入地下
and then comes out in steam vents all over the place.
然后从各处蒸汽口中冒出来
This is a nice aerial video from the US Geological Survey.
这是美国地质调查局提供的一个很好的航拍视频
It's a little old now
它现在有点旧了
and you can tell that it's old
你可以看出它是旧的
because the access road that was laid down by Mr. Carnivorous Plants dude isn't actually visible in this.
因为食肉植物先生铺设的通道在这段视频中实际上并不可见
But yeah you can see the structures here and that largely hasn't changed.
但是 你可以看到这里的结构 基本上没有改变
You can see that it has this sort of horseshoe shaped crater rim.
你可以看到 它有这种马蹄形的火山口边缘
The lava would flow out one side
熔岩会从一边流出来
and on the other side it would just land and weld itself into a very large structure
在另一边 熔岩会触地并形成一个非常大的结构
and that's what people are climbing up to get a look inside this.
这就是人们爬上去看里面的东西
This is absolutely wild.
这绝对是狂野的
这里是ʻAhuʻailāʻau的火山口，而不是基拉韦厄
I mean listen this was a huge vent spewing lava three years ago.
我的意思是听着 三年前这是一个巨大的喷口 喷出熔岩
And I mean odds are national parks aren't going to let me on this.
我的意思是 国家公园有可能不会让我进入这个地方
This is probably wild.
这可能是原始的
This is it.
就是这儿
That's the actual crater down there.
这就是下面的 实际的火山口
They had lava in there.
还有熔岩在那里
As it happens we reached the top around sunset
碰巧的是 我们在日落时分到达了山顶
and the light was still good enough to see the structure inside.
光线仍然很好 足以看到里面的结构
See all the different colors.
看到所有不同的颜色
Also see that the the floor has originally it was liquid lava
还可以看到 地板原本是液态熔岩
but it had frozen up and it actually collapsed in the middle.
但它已经凝固了 它实际上在中间塌陷了
That's quite common with lava lakes
这在熔岩湖中是很常见的
because as the lava drains out underneath
因为当熔岩从下面流走时
the crust no longer has anything underneath it to support it
地壳不再有任何东西在下面支撑它
and you'll have these collapsed structures
所以你就会有这些塌陷的结构
or sometimes you'll get things like lava tunnels and stuff like that.
或者有时你会得到像熔岩隧道之类的东西
Also I'm noticing a lot of debris has landed on top of the bottom of the crater here.
我还注意到很多碎片落在了火山口底部的顶部
That would mean that the sides are still sort of collapsing.
这就意味着两侧仍然在坍塌
Now in that area in the middle there's green stuff there.
现在在中间的那个区域 那里有绿色的东西
I am told that these are ferns
我被告知 这些是蕨类植物
which is quite impressive that they are already establishing themselves
令人印象深刻的是 它们就已经开始生长了
only a couple of years after this has really cooled down.
也就是这里才真正冷却下来的仅仅几年后
And looking down along the rift you can see some evidence of fissures one through seven there.
沿着裂缝向下看 你可以看到一至七号裂缝的一些证据
The fissures are all numbered in the order that they opened up.
这些裂缝都是按照它们开放的顺序编号的
and the first group were down there they ended up being less active.
第一组裂缝在下面 它们最终没有那么活跃
Number eight happened to be the one that was absolutely the most dominant.
第八条恰好是绝对最主要的一条
If you look off downstream then you'll see lots of this lava that has since hardened.
如果你往下游看 你会看到很多熔岩 后来都变硬了
It kind of looks like sheets that have been draped over the landscape
它看起来就像被覆盖在景观上的片状物
and that has flowed over the tephra fields.
并流过了火山灰土区
Now the tephra tends to only get formed when there's a lot of lava spraying up in the air
那么 只有当大量的熔岩喷到空中时 才会形成火山灰土
and it can be laid out uphill against gravity
而且它可以在上坡上逆着重力形成
whereas the liquid lava it will flow downhill.
而液态熔岩则会流向山下
It will cover any tephra that's been blown out early on
它将覆盖所有早期被喷出的火山灰土
and it will continue to flow long after the pressure drops below what's required to create lava fountains.
而且在压力下降到熔岩喷泉所需的程度之后  它还会继续流动
So that's why you've got different geology on both sides of this structure
所以这就是为什么在这个结构的两边有不同的地质情况
and off to the west there was another group of fissures that were evidenced by their steam emissions.
在西边 还有一组熔岩裂缝 它们滚滚排放出的蒸汽可以证明这一点
Also thanks to careful planning when we got up to the top it was sunset.
另外 由于精心策划 当我们登上山顶时 已是日落时分
And it was a spectacular sunset.
那是一个壮观的日落
This is one of these sunsets to remember kind of sunsets
这是一种值得纪念的日落
even if it wasn't for the fact that we were standing on top of
即使不是因为我们站在一个新近形成的地质结构的顶部
a very recently formed geological structure in a absolute wilderness of devastation.
一个最近形成的地质结构 在一个绝对荒芜的地方
Now returning to the top of Kilauea
现在回到基拉韦厄的顶部
as the eruption in 2018 drained most of the magma from the mountain the Caldera collapsed
由于2018年的火山爆发耗尽了大部分岩浆 原先的火山口坍塌了
and water began to come back in from leaking in through the ground
水开始从地面渗入 重新流入
and we had a lake farm which was very chemically rich.
我们有一个湖泊农场 它的化学成分非常丰富
And towards the end of 2020 a lava lake flowed back in there.
而在2020年底 一个熔岩湖又流回了那里
This was actually quite surprising
这实际上是相当令人惊讶的
because having so much magma drain out of the mountain it wasn't clear there'd be any reserves
因为有这么多的岩浆从山上流出来 本以为并没有更多的储备
and when my wife planned a vacation for June
当我的妻子计划在6月休假时
I was really hopeful that I was going to see some more lava flowing on the island
我真的希望能在岛上看到更多的熔岩流动
and as luck would have it, yeah the magma basically stopped flowing
但幸运的是 岩浆基本上停止了流动
and the crater lake solidified in maze.
而火山口湖在不规则的情况下凝固
I missed it by weeks.
我错过了几个星期的时间
it wasn't even looking that hot when I got there.
当我到达那里时 它看起来甚至没有那么热
But make no mistake even if Kilauea sleeps for a few years or decades.
但是不要搞错了 即使基拉韦厄沉睡了几年或几十年
In the long term it is still going to be very active.
从长远来看 它仍将是非常活跃的
In fact probably the most active volcano in the world.
事实上 它可能是世界上最活跃的火山
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]